Polling and sleeping between new messages
is wasteful, tricky, and hard to scale.
XREAD's real power is that it can
be coded in blocking manner, effectively abolishing
the need for consumers to poll.
In this unit, we'll learn how to do that.
Generally, Redis's blocking commands
are so named because they block the Redis client's execution.
Redis lists and sorted sets, for example,
provide a blocking pop operation that
can wait for new elements and members
to be stored in an empty data structure.
Similarly, pub/sub subscriptions are also blocking.
The subscribing Redis client waits for new messages
to arrive over channels, and is essentially
blocked until they do.
Streams also provide a blocking way
to consume messages with the optional BLOCK sub-command
that XREAD accepts.
When used with BLOCK, XREAD will either return immediately
with up to COUNT messages in the input streams
if there are any, or will block execution
for the specified number of milliseconds before timing out.
If new messages are added to any of the streams
during the block period, XREAD will return these.
However, in that case, COUNT will always be 1.
Let's try that in the CLI.
First, we'll make sure that our static natural numbers
stream is ready.
Then, for demonstration purposes,
I'll use XRANGE to get the final two messages in the stream,
so I have IDs to use with XREAD.
When we call the command with the second-to-last message ID,
despite being provided with a full second to block,
XREAD immediately returns.
This is because it was able to fetch the next,
and in our case, the last, message in the stream.
However, calling XREAD again with the ID
of the last message in the stream
puts it into blocking mode, because there
are no new messages after that.
After a second has passed, and because no new numbers were
added, XREAD times out, and Redis returns the nil response
to signal that.
Like other Redis subcommands that
accept a timeout, 0 is a valid but dangerous value.
0 is interpreted as "block forever,"
and you don't really want to do that in the real world.
An infinite timeout, on the other hand,
is a very handy tool in demonstrating how a blocking
XREAD call is unblocked.
In the first terminal window, I call
XREAD with an infinite timeout.
This gives me all the time in the world
to switch to another terminal window and type
the XADD command.
During that time, the XREAD is blocking the client
until the server sends a reply.
It took me slightly less than 20 seconds
to add the new message in the other terminal.
The instant it was added,
Redis had also sent it to the XREADing client,
effectively unblocking it.
Some programs will need to process the entire stream
at once, but others may only need
to get new messages to do their work.
Another type of consumer, perhaps more common,
is one that only listens to new messages.
In the previous example, I used XREVRANGE to retrieve
the last message ID in the stream, which I then
used as input for XREAD.
While effective, this pattern involves two calls,
and could be streamlined using only XREAD, plus yet
another special message ID.
To start an XREAD operation from the next new message
in the stream, pass in the dollar sign character ("$")
as the message ID.
The special dollar sign message ID ("$")
is a shortcut that tells Redis to use the last message.
So with it, I can subscribe to the stream
and will then receive any new message from there
on out, until the timeout is triggered.
The special dollar message ID should
be used, however, only for fetching the first new message.
Once the first new message has been read,
we want to move on to the next new message.
But remember, that it is possible that more than one message
has been added to the stream.
To ensure that new messages aren't skipped over,
subsequent calls should use the last-processed ID.
This pattern allows the consumer to begin its processing
at the first new message and then
process all messages after it.
Armed with this knowledge, I can now implement an efficient
running sum that blocks and listens for new messages,
instead of polling for them.
It uses a blocking XREAD and employs
a basic exponential back-off mechanism to handle timeouts.
When I run it on the static natural numbers stream,
this is what it looks like.
Note that after consuming all the messages
and then politely retrying to wait for new ones,
this process eventually quits.
We can provide a continuous stream to the consumer
by reverting to our original producer code.
I'll start by flushing the database and then starting
producer_1.py.
Then, in a different session, I can run the consumer.
This time, the consumer will continue
to run until the producer, or the consumer, itself are stopped.
The blocking consumer pattern is a reason for XREAD's existence.
There is no "XREVREAD", because that does not
align with our current interpretation
of the arrow of time.
Blocking consumer can begin consuming one or more streams
at any arbitrary position.
However, the blocking pattern is especially
suitable for consumers that process
new messages as they arrive.