You've now arrived at the end of week two of our course
on Redis streams.
This week we saw how to create and populate
streams using a producer, as well as
how to read from them using consumers and range queries.
As streams and Pub/Sub provide some overlapping functionality
in Redis, we also spent some time
looking at important differences between the two.
The course continues next week when
we'll take a deep dive into the creation and management
of consumer groups.
You'll learn the Redis way of organizing and managing
multiple consumers so that they can work together
to process streaming data.
As part of that, we'll also look at how to manage and recover
from situations where a consumer may fail,
and messages may need to be reassigned
to others for processing.
Thanks for spending the time with us.
We'll see you again next week.