We've seen how streams are made up
of messages that are in turn generated by producers that
can later be read proactively using the range
commands XRANGE and XREVRANGE.
And while ranges are useful for batch processing,
we've also seen how range queries
can be used to process the stream in near-real-time.
Real time consumption is what stream consumers are
all about and in this section, we'll
learn about an even more effective way
to consume our stream in real time.
Let's start the discussion by recalling
how the running sum of natural numbers was implemented.
Every call to range_sum.py
retrieves or initializes a hash storing the last message
ID and sum.
The code then scans all messages in the stream,
sums them up, and stores the results back into the hash.
The amount of actual work done by our code
is dictated by the stream's growth and the number of yet-
to-be-processed messages in it.
As long as we keep calling it fast enough,
our sum will be accurate.
Fast enough is an interesting concept related to time.
Fast enough in our case means faster than any new messages
are added to the stream.
To achieve that.
We could try and wrap the logic inside an infinite loop.
But then most times, we'd just waste calls on empty ranges
and increase the server's load.
Besides being wasteful, this pattern
will limit our ability to scale the consumers significantly
because every consumer will be competing
with all others on the server's resources
by incessantly polling it.
On the other hand, if we call this code any slower,
for example, by sleeping for a second between each call,
not only will our sum's accuracy be off, but also
consider the possibility of a variable workload.
If the producer is jittering, one call
may sum just a couple of numbers where
another may add a big bunch.
This will naturally effect our consumer's code execution time.
And such unpredictabilities could result in bottlenecks
down the road.
So, as a further optimization we may
consider using smaller batches-- that is, the size of one--
and sleeping only when there are no new messages.
This will get us close in terms of accuracy
and runtime predictability, but would still
use wasteful and not so scalable polling logic.
Sleeping is also a non-productive activity,
although it frees the client's cores,
it prevents it from receiving and processing
any new messages that may come in during its slumber.
One-message batches are commonly used
not only because of their semi- predictable processing impact
but also because in many cases messages
can be processed independently one from another
which paves the way to scaling.
We've already met the COUNT sub command
that allows us to restrict the reply from both XRANGE
and XREVRANGE.
It can be used exactly for that.
Now, I'd like to introduce you to another Redis
stream command:
XREAD.
Superficially, XREAD can be used as a drop-in replacement
for XRANGE.
I can, for example, fetch the entire stream like so, just
by providing the name of the stream and the message
ID to begin with, or 0 for the lowest partial message ID.
It is important to note that XREAD does not take
the special IDs "-" or "+".
These are exclusively and solely used by range queries.
XREAD also supports the optional COUNT argument,
so I can use it for iterating the stream at any batch
resolution, just like XRANGE.
In fact, I can modify my code to use XREAD instead of XRANGE
for keeping the running sum while keeping
the rest of the logic pretty much the same.
But, XREAD offers much more than XRANGE does
and the differences, although subtle,
are incredibly important.
The first difference between how XREAD and XRANGE work
is the message ID that XREAD expects.
The ID is actually the last message ID
known to the consumer, which means that Redis will respond
with messages whose IDs are greater than the one provided.
This is unlike XRANGE's inclusive ranges,
which force us to perform complex message ID
arithmetic in order to come up with the next message ID.
Put slightly differently, XREAD's reply
will consist of up to COUNT messages that have
arrived after the requested ID.
I can use either the partial ID 0 or the 0-0 ID
to specify the message prior to the first message
in the stream.
The reply includes the message IDs,
so to continue iterating the stream,
I just copy the last message ID from the reply
to the next call.
That means that the consumer only
needs to track the last ID that it had processed
and carry that from one call to another.
Much simpler.
Cool.
Another difference you may have noticed
is the use of the STREAMS keyword when calling XREAD.
While COUNT is optional, STREAMS isn't.
STREAMS precedes the list of stream key names,
in plural, followed by a list of respective message IDs.
In our example, we've used XREAD to read from a single stream,
but it can actually be used to read from multiple ones.
Because XREAD is a multi-key command
the reply returned differs from that of XRANGE,
in that it includes the stream's key name alongside each list
of returned messages.
This allows us to associate each part of the reply
with the relevant input stream.
Before we move on to what really makes XREAD special,
let's summarize what we've learned so far.
Both XRANGE and XREAD can be used to iterate a stream.
By using the smallest possible batch size, that is,
one message, a consumer's execution time
can be made semi-predictable.