Let's take a few minutes to review
the differences between the Redis Streams and Redis
Pub/Sub.
Pub/Sub, which is short for Publish/Subscribe,
is just what the name implies, a Redis construct
for publishing messages to any and all subscribers.
Under this paradigm, both senders and recipients
are oblivious to each other.
They simply agree on a channel for communication of messages.
The senders publish messages to channels,
without knowing who is going to receive them.
Similarly, receivers subscribe to the channels that interest
them but are not assured that there
are any publishers on the other side.
Of course, channels may have any number
of publishers and consumers.
This makes Pub/Sub a common pattern
to allow dynamic scaling of a distributed system.
The Pub/Sub messaging paradigm in Redis
is exposed via the PUBLISH and SUBSCRIBE commands.
Subscribers are blocked as long as there are no new messages
and are immediately messaged and freed as soon
as a publisher sends news.
With Pub/Sub, subscribers can only
start listening for new messages.
In other words, a Pub/Sub channel
doesn't store any messages.
Messages are published immediately to all subscribers
and are then forever lost.
You can implement the Pub/Sub paradigm with Redis Streams,
but there are a few important differences.
First, a stream entry is semi-structured,
whereas Pub/Sub's is just a string.
Second, each stream message has an ID,
whereas Pub/Sub messages don't.
Besides the embedded temporal information that a stream entry
ID carries, we've seen how we can use these IDs to access
messages in the stream.
Next, unlike a Pub/Sub channel, a stream actually stores data.
In other words, the messages in a stream
are stored so that they can later be retrieved and processed
by a variety of consumers.
So let's think delivery semantics for a moment.
You really need to think of Redis Pub/Sub as a fire-
and-forget mechanism.
Formally speaking, it has at-most-once message delivery
semantics.
If a subscriber has crashed, or if the network has failed,
or if, for any other reason, the message was not delivered,
there's no way to retrieve it.
For cases where at-most-once delivery is inadequate,
Redis Streams is a better alternative.
Using a Redis Streams consumer, you can always mimic
the at-most-once semantics of Redis Pub/Sub by using
the special "$" ID, which will retrieve only the latest
messages.
But by keeping track of the message ID that it receives,
the consumer can also pick up where it left off.
The ID could be stored only locally,
in the consumer's memory, or persisted somehow,
to Redis for example, for process-failure resilience
purposes.
This way, with Redis Streams, you
can implement an at-least-once message delivery semantics.
The table on screen provides a concise summary
of the differences between Redis Pub/Sub and Redis Streams.
So what's the upshot?
You should use Redis Pub/Sub when
you need a lightweight channel to deliver messages
to a number of subscribers.
If this is all you need, the simplicity of Redis Pub/Sub
is a win over Redis Streams.
However, if you need at-least-once semantics,
ID-based access to messages,
a structured key value format,
or fine grained control over your message consumption,
then Redis Streams is the way to go.