We've focused our discussion, up until now,
on how to use Redis Streams to feed a single consumer.
But one of the more useful properties of streams
is their ability to support multiple concurrent blocking
consumers.
When multiple consumers are listening
for new messages in a given stream,
every new message is sent to every connected blocking
consumer in a pattern known as "fan-out."
Having multiple blocking consumers
to fan-out stream messages is a useful, event-driven scaling
pattern.
We can use it to parallelize processing
by breaking the processing into multiple concurrent tasks that
execute asynchronously.
Each blocking consumer operates independently from the rest,
in terms of the logic it needs to run
and the resources that it uses.
All blocking consumers, however, view the same stream
and are waiting for the same messages to arrive.
Once each consumer finishes its workload,
it can re-enter the blocking read state to
process the next message.
We can demonstrate this orchestrated multi-consumption
with a new type of consumer that chases the tip
of the natural numbers stream.
The new consumer type will check whether the data
is divisible by a given number.
One instance of the consumer will
check whether the number can be divided
by two without a remainder.
And another instance would then perform a similar check
for divisibility by three.
Both consumers will be running in parallel
and will be processing the same messages, although perhaps
not at the same time.
Instead of using multiple terminals, in this example,
we'll use subprocesses to simplify launching it.
One subprocess is the producer which
is set to stop producing after the first eight messages,
for demonstration purposes.
Two other subprocesses are the consumers,
each performing a different calculation
on the message's payload.
While the order of output lines may vary between runs,
you can see the asynchronous and somewhat chaotic nature
of this setup.
The producer produces at its own pace,
sometimes spitting out new messages faster
than any consumer can process them.
At the same time, consumer instances
work in parallel, through the stream, each processing
a message at a time, possibly blocking
while waiting for new ones.
Having multiple concurrent consumers subscribe
to all new messages from one or more streams
is a pattern for processing the same data in multiple ways.
Data is effectively broadcasted to all subscribers,
thus triggering their respective activities.
We can use this pattern for scaling
the processing of complex tasks by breaking these
into multiple, asynchronous subtasks that
are easier to perform by many cheaper resources.