Thanks again for being part of this course.
We hope you've enjoyed it, and we
hope it's provided you with the tools you need to successfully
use Redis Streams.
If you pass the course with a grade of 65% or greater,
please see the next steps for generating your certificate
and posting it to your LinkedIn profile.
And if you have any feedback or insights
you want to share with the Redis University team,
don't hesitate to leave a note on the discussion forums.
We'll also be sending out a survey
in the near future, where you can leave comments and help
us to improve future versions of Redis Streams.
Again, we're grateful you've taken the time
to work through this Redis University course.
Happy learning, and see you next time.