You've now completed all the video tutorials, quizzes,
and homework.
You're almost to the finishing line.
The last week of the course will be your final exam.
The final exam counts for 50% of your grade.
You have a week to complete this exam,
so take your time to read and answer the questions carefully.
After you've submitted your answers,
you'll be graded automatically.
If you receive a final grade of 65% or more,
then you'll earn a certificate of completion.
Instructions are provided at the end of this chapter
to generate and view your certificate, along
with how to add the certificate to your LinkedIn profile.
And don't forget that the forums are still
available if you have any questions or need assistance.
Thanks for sticking with it so far
and good luck with the exam.