We've seen how messages are identified
in a stream with their IDs.
So let's talk about their contents now.
Every message in the stream contains data.
The data, as far as Redis is concerned,
is opaque and can be anything that the producer provides.
Redis does not assume anything about the data
you store in the stream but, rather, provides ordered
access to it efficiently.
In the previous examples, we've seen
how XADD expects data arguments to be
field-value tuples, similarly to how Redis's hashes behave.
Empty messages are not allowed, so every message
has to have at least one field-value pair.
But you can use any number of fields up to some arbitrary
power of 2 to construct it.
Each value in a field name is a plain old regular Redis string
capable of storing up to half a gigabyte of data.
The actual data can be a simple numerical value,
such as a sensor's reading, a string representing an order
confirmation number, a compressed JSON
document, or any other type of serialization format.
The data itself is opaque to Redis,
meaning that the server does not attempt
to process it in any way.
The field names, however, undergo a compression of sorts
in order to optimize the total memory footprint of the stream
data structure.
Field-name compression kicks in automatically
when consecutive messages in the stream
share the same field names.
In such cases, Redis will avoid storing the actual names
repeatedly for new messages and, instead,
uses pointer-like logic.
Because in a lot of streams, the message's format
remains constant while only the data changes,
this on-the-fly optimization eliminates
redundant duplication of the metadata.
Don't worry too much, however, if field-name compression
is not applicable in your use case.
Like other Redis identifiers, just
strive to keep your field names short and descriptive-ish.
At this point, it is important to understand
that when read, messages are always returned as a whole.
Redis commands that read from streams
return the full messages without filtering or allowing
field-level selection.
So if you're storing a combination
of tiny and large fields, don't assume
that you can optimize the response's size
by selecting only the small fields.
Let's summarize what we've learned in this video.
Data is stored in stream messages
as a collection of fields and their values.
Values are Redis strings, so they
can contain texts or numerical values
as well as any serialized data.
When consecutive messages share the same fields,
Redis uses in-flight compression to reduce their memory
footprint.