Up until now, we've seen how streams
are produced with the Redis stream producer API.
The Redis stream API also includes other commands
and provides introspection of the data structure.
One such introspective command reports back to us
the length of a stream stored at a given key.
It is called XLEN.
Recall that earlier, we created the natural numbers stream
with two messages.
We can verify that there are, indeed,
only two messages with XLEN.
Like many other Redis data structures,
all stream commands share a common prefix.
Why we chose the letter X, in this case,
is left as an exercise for you.
XLEN expects a single argument, the stream's key name,
and returns the total number of messages
in it (or its current length).
A non-existent key, like other data structures,
will have a length of 0.
But unlike any other data structure in Redis,
a stream can have a length of zero, and its key will still exist.
There are several ways that a Redis stream can be empty --
that is, for its key to exist without a data structure
containing any messages.
We can demonstrate that with another useful stream
command, XDEL.
As its name suggests, XDEL deletes messages from streams.
Specifically, it operates on a single stream
given by its first argument, and one or more message IDs to
delete. In the example, we provided
XDEL with the two message IDs.
After execution, the Redis server
replies with the total number of messages that were actually
deleted from the stream.
Note that while checking the stream's length
yields the expected 0, calling EXISTS on it, proves
that it does.
Of course, with stream values being just keys,
we can use them with non-data-structure-specific
commands, too.
For example, we can see that the overall memory
footprint of the empty number stream is 293 bytes in total.
To remove the entire, empty or not, stream,
we can just call DEL or UNLINK on it,
like any other Redis key.
However, this unusual ability of the stream data structure--
and by unusual, I mean that in comparison to other data
structures in Redis--
to exist without data is used by other parts of the API
that we'll discuss shortly.
XDEL can be useful for surgically removing the odd
message from a stream for any conceivable purpose.
It should be also noted that the memory that
was used for storing the messages deleted by it
is not always reclaimed in Redis version
5, although that may change in the future.
It is, however, quite impractical
to use XDEL as a way to control the stream's length,
as it requires you to know the IDs of every message you
want to remove,
Depending on the volume of messages produced and stored
in it, a stream may grow indefinitely
in length, while performance is independent of the stream's
length, the longer the stream grows, the more
memory that it will require.
And while in some cases, this may be the required behavior,
in others, it is possible to limit the stream's length.
To keep streams from running indefinitely and infinitely,
or leaking, Redis allows trimming them,
an operation also known as truncation.
That allows capping their length at a specified number.
The underlying assumption when trimming messages
is, of course, that they can be safely removed from the stream.
That is, these messages have been processed
and/or can be discarded.
There's more than one way to trim a stream,
and XTRIM is the most obvious way.
Given the name of the stream and the maximum length,
or MAXLEN for short.
It will trim all but the latest MAXLEN messages.
When trimming the stream to a certain size,
Redis will reclaim the memory previously held
by the purged entries.
However, because of how the data structure is implemented
internally, trimming a stream to an exact size
may be expensive performance-wise.
So Redis allows two types of trimming,
a close shave that leaves the stream at exactly
the requested length, or a rough cut that
only approximates the attempt.
In this example, we show how to use XTRIM for a close shave.
The reason for using a multi-exec block in the example
is to capture the streaming in a moment of time
as the producer keeps producing indefinitely.
The reply it returns --
the second element in our transaction's reply --
is the number of messages that were removed.
Performing a rough cut or an approximate trimming,
which is a more efficient operation,
performance-wise, is just a matter
of putting a tilde character before MAXLEN's value
when calling XTRIM.
Doing so instructs Redis to optimize for efficient memory
management over the exactness of the truncation,
so the resulting length of the string
will be either equal or larger than the MAXLEN,
but not significantly so.
You can call XTRIM periodically, but it is also
possible to have its functionality invoked directly
from XADD.
When used with the optional MAXLEN sub-command,
as shown in the example, Redis will automatically
trim the stream after appending the new message to it.
The choice between periodical and per-message trimming
is yours to make.
Per-message trimming will keep the stream constantly capped,
whereas periodical trimming will make its size
variable over time.
Another thing to note is that trimming
is a synchronous operation with linear time-complexity.
So the more messages trimmed, the longer
it will take to complete.