In this chapter, we'll discuss the stream producer interface
and the way in which messages are structured.
This stream is a data structure, and the data
stored in it are messages.
The messages are written to the stream by software components.
Such components are called stream producers,
as they produce new messages, and therefore
the stream itself.
From a high-level perspective, the stream producer
integrates use-case-specific logic
with the Redis stream producer API.
Generally, a producer reads data from one or more sources
and then writes it to the stream, possibly
after transforming it in the process.
So a producer can be very simple, very complex,
or anywhere in between.
It all depends on the system that it operates in.
For example, a simple producer may
be embedded inside an IoT temperature sensor.
The sensor periodically samples the current temperature
readings and then appends the raw values
to the "temperatures" Redis stream.
In such a setup, it is conceivable
that there are many, perhaps hundreds
or thousands of such producers.
In another context, such as that of a shopping site implemented
with micro-services, producers may be any of the services
that power the site.
For example, the order confirmation
micro-service can store each confirmed order Redis stream
to facilitate further processing,
such as sending an email.
While a part of the producer component that
generates the data is quite open-ended,
the part that writes it to a Redis stream
is always the same.
All Redis stream producers use the Redis Stream Producer
API, which consists of a single all-purpose command.
In the following units, we'll learn
about adding messages, identifying messages,
the data in messages and managing
the stream's length.