The producer API allows a producer
to append an arbitrary message to a Redis stream.
In this unit, we'll introduce that interface, and the manner
in which it should be used.
The Redis stream producer interface
is made up of a single command, XADD,
that the producer calls with the explicit name of the stream.
That is, the key's name, and the message's payload or data.
Let's look at an example to understand
how a producer operates.
To make the producer extremely simple to reason about,
our stream's data will be the sequence of natural numbers
as defined by ISO 80000-2.
These are all the numbers beginning with 0
that correspond to the non-negative
integers 0, 1, 2, and so forth.
To start the stream, the producer
will add a message with a single field.
Let's call it "n", that contains the first number
in the sequence, that is 0.
This is how you do that in the CLI.
We've called XADD with several arguments, where
the first one, numbers, is the name of the key
at which the stream is stored.
The name of the stream's key is the contract
between your stream's producers and consumers.
And it is implicitly created if it doesn't exist,
like all other Redis data structures.
Note that XADD is a single key command, so a message is always
added to a single stream.
The second argument to XADD is the new message's ID.
In most cases, we want Redis to manage the generation
of message IDs.
In fact, one of the compelling reasons to use a stream
is for its inherent ordering of messages, which is achieved
by having Redis manage it.
By setting the ID argument to an asterisk, as in our example,
we let Redis generate the ID for the new message.
The ID is returned as XADD's reply,
and we'll get to that in the next unit.
The remainder of the arguments are the actual data.
They are provided as pairs of field names and their values,
exactly like how HSET is used with Redis' hashes.
And just like Redis' hashes, every value and field
name in the message is a Redis string.
A Redis string can store up to half a gigabyte
of binary-safe data if needed, although messages usually
tend to be much shorter.
Adding in the next message, that is the number
1, to the stream of natural numbers,
is just another call to XADD.
The automatic generation of IDs guarantees their uniqueness.
And the order of arrival of messages
determines their position in the stream.
Before moving on to other aspects of the XADD command,
I'd like to spend a few seconds reviewing its performance.
Redis is all about providing low latency, predictable
performance when manipulating its data structures.
And the stream is no different in that respect.
With XADD being the most common write operation,
the data structure is designed and implemented in such a way
that it provides constant sub millisecond latency,
whether the stream has 137 messages in it or 42 billion.
That's also known as O(1)
in terms of asymptotic computational complexity.
Let's recap.
While Redis stream producers vary greatly
in terms of the domain-specific logic that they implement,
all use the XADD command to append new messages
to the stream data structure.
XADD expects the stream key name and ID and the message's data,
it executes in constant time, regardless of the stream size,
and replies with the message ID.