Let's give the message identifier a closer look.
In our CLI example, the producer's invocations of XADD
were replied with a message identifier.
Every successful call to the Redis Streams producer API,
a.k.a, XADD, returns the newly added message's identifier,
or ID for short.
The ID is unique, and every message
has exactly one and only one ID.
Once created, a message's ID is immutable
and bound to the message's position inside the stream.
Messages with lower IDs will be closer
to the beginning of the stream, whereas the higher IDs
will occur later in the stream.
As we've seen before, Redis can generate message IDs
automatically when instructed to do so with the asterisk ID
argument.
Let's use a little-known CLI feature to take a closer look
at these auto-generated IDs.
We'll generate several, seven, to be precise,
dummy messages in quick succession, and XADD them
to a stream just to see how their IDs look.
Here we've called XADD seven times with the same message.
Each time we've called it, the message was added to the stream
and assigned with a new, auto-magically generated ID.
An inspection of the IDs reveals that each ID
is made of exactly two numbers,
separated by a dash.
The first number in the message ID
is a millisecond-resolution timestamp.
When auto-generated, these values are
obtained from the Redis server's clock.
Redis ensures that the timestamp part of the ID never decreases.
Consider, for example, a case in which the server is restarted,
and its clock is rewound.
Under these circumstances, Redis will revert
to using the maximal timestamp of the stream instead
of the current clock reading to prevent
any time-travel-like phenomenon.
Internally, the timestamp part of an ID
is stored by Redis as an unsigned 64-bit integer.
This means that we can comfortably
accommodate all the milliseconds until
about, oh, 300 million years into the future.
The second part of the message ID
is an internal sequence kept by Redis
that provides sub-millisecond resolution, because it
is possible for multiple messages
to be added inside the span of a single millisecond,
the Redis server appends that sequence to message IDs
to ensure their uniqueness and guarantee their order.
The sequence is reset to zero with every new millisecond,
as can be viewed in the example.
The sequence is guaranteed to always increase.
And like the timestamp, it is implemented
as an unsigned 64-bit integer.
For your information, that's enough capacity
for over 9 quintillion messages per millisecond,
just in case you were wondering.
So, Redis's auto-generated IDs are
more than capable to accommodate any number
of incoming messages.
However, in some cases, producers
may require absolute control over the messages' order.
And will therefore require the ability
to explicitly specify IDs.
Generally, this is required when an external mechanism
is used to collect and enforce the order of incoming messages
before they are appended to the stream.
In such cases, it is up to the producers
to supply the message ID, instead
of having Redis generate them and ensure that the IDs are
always increasing.
Let's take a look at a synthetic example
with dummy data in the CLI.
The producer can assign any valid message ID
to a message added with XADD as long as the lowest
possible message ID is 0-1, and any subsequent message IDs
are greater than the stream's current maximum message ID.
This CLI snippet demonstrates how a producer
can specify the message ID.
In the case of the new stream, we
can begin adding messages using any legitimate ID,
starting from 0-1, or as in the example,
an arbitrary value such as 127.
Any message ID can be used as long
as it is greater than the stream's current maximal ID.
Partial IDs -- that is to say, IDs
without the sequence component -- are also valid as arguments.
Partial IDs are interpreted as if the sequence
part is implicitly set to 0.
1337 is, therefore, a valid partial ID, with its sequence
counter defaulting to 0, because it
is greater than any of the IDs previously defined.
Note, however, how the server rejects the message
with an ID of 123-6379, and responds with an error message.
That is because we tried adding a message with an ID
that's lower than the stream's current maximal ID.
To recap, every message in the stream has a unique identifier.
The ID can be either supplied by the producer
or automatically generated by Redis.
IDs are unique and are made up of two parts,
a millisecond-resolution timestamp
and an internal sequence.
The IDs of messages in the stream are always increasing,
and new messages always have IDs higher than older ones.