With the ever-growing need to process
more and more real-time streaming data,
it was only natural for Redis to add support
for a stream-like data structure.
This feature, officially known as Redis Streams,
was released in October 2018 with Redis 5.0.
In this chapter, I'm going to give you
an overview of Redis Streams, describing the features that
make them unique.
Redis Streams is a sophisticated feature.
But you can make sense of it by understanding
the following main ideas--
first, Redis Streams is essentially a new Redis data
structure.
This data structure is known as a stream.
Second, the stream behaves like an append-only list or log.
Third, each entry in a stream is structured
as a set of key value pairs.
So you can think of a stream entry
as something akin to a Redis hash.
Fourth, every stream entry has a unique ID.
And by default, these IDs are time-prefixed.
Fifth, streams support ID-based range queries.
And finally, streams can be consumed and processed
by multiple distinct sets of consumers.
These are known as consumer groups.
Now, that's a lot to unpack.
So let's look at each of these ideas one by one.
First, Redis Streams is a new Redis data structure.
Like all Redis data structures, each Redis Stream
is addressed with a key.
And that key points to a value of type stream.
What this means is that you can use
all of the standard key operations
against keys that point to a stream.
For instance, you can use the del command to delete a stream.
And you can use the expire command
to set a time to live or TTL.
TTL's are, of course, incredibly powerful and often essential
for keeping streaming data sets from growing too large.
The next idea is that a stream acts like an append-only log.
In other words, the only way to put data into a stream
is to add it to the end.
This, in fact, nicely fits a common definition of streams
as an ordered or semi-ordered series of events.
Streams are also immutable.
That is, the ordering of entries cannot be changed.
However, Redis does allow stream entries to be deleted.
And that will be discussed in a later chapter of this course.
The third idea is that each stream entry
is structured as a set of key value pairs
just like a Redis hash.
For instance, you could create a weather-based stream
containing fields for temperature, humidity,
barometric pressure, and location.
The next idea is that each entry in a Redis Stream
has a unique ID.
By default, these ideas consist of a timestamp prefix
and a sequence number suffix.
So stream entries are effectively indexed by time.
What's more is that stream support range queries.
When you combine this with time prefixed IDs,
you get time-based range queries.
In other words, I can read and process all stream events
from a particular time range.
To go back to our earlier example,
suppose we're collecting weather readings.
If we've been collecting this data over a period of time,
and we want to reprocess the data from midnight UTC
January 1 to 2:00 AM January 1, well, Redis Streams
can make that happen.
The final major feature of Redis Streams
is its support for consumer groups.
A consumer group is a set of one or more consumers
that, together, process the stream in its entirety.
For instance, here's a picture of a stream.
And here are it's consumer groups.
Notice that each consumer group processes
the stream in its entirety.
So really, you can think of a consumer
group as akin to a subscriber in a pub/sub system.
And so to create a consumer group
is to create something like a subscriber
to a particular stream.
The difference with consumer groups
is that each group may divide its consumption of the stream
among a number of consumer instances.
You can see how that looks in the diagram here.
Notice that each group consists of a few consumers.
Consumer groups give us a lot of flexibility
in the way we process a stream.
For example, consumer groups allow
us to easily syndicate data across
multiple internal systems.
In the diagram here, you can see that we're
sending all of our weather data to three separate systems--
first, to a data warehouse, second,
to a machine learning pipeline, and lastly, to a notification
system.
We can also use consumer groups to construct
arbitrarily-complex processing topologies or stream pipelines.
We'll be discussing all of this in much more detail
later in the course.
So you should now have a good high-level understanding
of Redis Streams.
To summarize, Redis Streams is a sophisticated new Redis data
structure.
As a Redis data structure, it's easy to create and destroy.
And a lot of the patterns that apply
to the management of any Redis key also
apply to keys that point to streams.
But with their support for ID-based access, range queries,
and consumer groups, Redis Streams
provide you with a lot of the primitives
you need to build modern streaming applications.