Well, you've finished your first week of Redis Streams.
We've covered what we hope is a lot of exciting new material.
Itamar started off the course
with a broad introduction to distributed systems,
stream processing, and streaming pipelines.
This essential background paved the way
for a general introduction to Redis Streams.
There I presented some of the main features of Redis Streams.
And I tried to show how Redis Streams compares to other Redis
data structures.
We also studied a working example
of Redis Streams written in Python.
Having completed this introduction,
it's now it's time to get down to brass tacks.
Next week, we'll start to describe
producers, range queries, and consumers in great detail.
Then in week 3, you'll learn everything
you ever wanted to know about consumer
groups and their management.
Looking forward to having you along.