In the last two videos, you got a high level introduction
to Redis Streams.
To complete this introduction and finish giving you
the big picture, I'm going to show you
a working example of Redis Streams using the Python
programming language.
In particular, we're going to write three programs.
The first is a producer that simulates
a stream of weather events being recorded in a Redis stream.
The next program is the logic for a consumer
group that writes the stream to a data warehouse.
And last is a consumer group that
calculates a moving temperature average for a live display.
I'll run these three programs in parallel,
and you'll get a sense of how Redis Streams can
work in action.
Let's get started with the producer.
First, we connect to the Redis server.
This step should be familiar.
Next, we set the name of the key for the stream
we'll be writing to.
In this case, it's stream colon weather.
We also initialize a Measurement object,
which will generate successive temperature measurements.
Next, we enter a loop.
On the first line, we get the next entry
to write to the stream.
This entry contains a postal code and a temperature
in Fahrenheit.
Next, we write the entry to the stream, and what gets returned
is the entry's ID.
We print this info to the screen,
and then we sleep for one second.
You can run the script like so, and you
should get output that looks something like this.
Now let's take a look at the first consumer group.
This consumer simulates the writing of the stream's data
to a data warehouse.
The hardest part about setting up a consumer group
is getting all of the settings just right.
Here we're assigning each setting to a variable.
First, we set the name of the stream.
Next we choose a consumer group name.
It's always best to choose a descriptive name.
And in this case, we're calling our group "data_warehouse_writer".
Now recall that a consumer group can
consist of more than one individual consumer.
For example, you might create one consumer per thread.
But in the interest of simplicity,
we're going to have just a single consumer named like so.
Next, we set the number of milliseconds to block for,
and we create an object that represents the stream
we want to read from and where we want to start in the stream.
We then ensure that the group has been created,
and we enter the loop where we read the results
and write them out to the data warehouse.
Notice now that the producer is still running.
Now I'm going to start the consumer we just created.
And as you can see, it's consuming the stream
and simulating the writes to the data warehouse.
OK, so real quickly, let's write the code that
runs the second consumer group.
As you can see, we first connect to Redis.
Then we set up all the variables that we
created in the last consumer.
The only difference here is that we use a different consumer
group name.
This group will be called "rolling_average_printer".
Everything else should be familiar.
We ensure that the group has been created.
Then we enter the loop and print the rolling average
after each read.
Now I'm going to run this consumer.
Notice first that I still have the producer running,
and I have the first consumer running.
So here's the second consumer.
And you can see that it's now printing the rolling average as
expected.
So that's it for our example.
If you want to play with this code on your own,
it's available in the virtual lab environment.
There are also instructions for downloading it
on the course setup page.