In the previous unit, I described
some of the key features of Redis Streams.
But to give you an even better idea of how Redis Streams fits
into the complete family of Redis data structures,
it's useful to make a few comparisons.
Specifically there are three axes
we can look at to compare Redis Streams to other Redis data
structures.
The first is blocking versus non-blocking commands.
The second is mutability.
And the third is storage and delivery,
especially as it relates to Redis Pub/Sub.
Let's take each of these in turn.
When we talk here about blocking versus non-blocking,
we're specifically referring to the question
of whether a Redis command returns immediately
or blocks until new data is available.
We're not talking about blocking versus non-blocking I/O,
otherwise known as async I/O, which is a lower-level concern
and beyond the scope of this course.
Anyway, as you probably already know,
most Redis commands don't block.
If I called get on a key that doesn't exist,
Redis returns immediately with a nil response.
It doesn't block.
Similarly, if I call lpop on an empty list,
Redis again returns a nil response.
For example, here, I'm pushing a single value onto a list.
I then pop it off with LPOP.
Now the list is empty.
When I call LPOP again, the command returns right away.
Now, when dealing with lists, we also
have the option of using a blocking command.
LPOP has a sister command called BLPOP,
and this version of the command blocks
for a specified period of time.
So see here, again, how I add a single element to a list.
I then run BLPOP, specifying a time-out of 30 seconds.
The first time I run this, BLPOP returns immediately.
But if I run it again BLPOP blocks for 30 seconds,
waiting for new data to appear in the list.
As with lists, Redis Streams gives you
the option to process a stream in both non-blocking
and blocking modes.
This gives you a lot of flexibility
in the way you can design your applications.
Now let's briefly talk about mutability.
A data structure is mutable when the contents of the structure
can be changed after being inserted.
Generally speaking, Redis data structures are mutable.
For example, I can modify the contents of a hash
after the fact using the HSET command.
Here, I'm creating a hash, and now I'm
changing one of the hash keys.
Or to take another example, here I'm
creating a new list of names.
And with this new list, I can insert a new element
into the middle of the list, like so.
Here, I'm adding the name Sue before Alice.
And here, I'm replacing the name Bob with Bill.
Clearly, hashes and lists are mutable.
So what about Redis Streams?
It turns out that with streams, mutability
is quite a bit more limited.
Generally speaking, you should think
of a stream as an append-only data structure.
When writing to a stream, you write to the end only.
There's no ability to insert into the middle of a stream
or to replace stream entries.
Also, the stream entries themselves cannot be modified,
even though these entries are structured like a hash.
But streams are mutable in the following two ways.
First, you can delete entries from a stream.
Now, it's important to note that when you delete a stream entry,
Redis will internally mark the entry as deleted.
This means that the entry won't be physically removed
from the stream, but it will never
be delivered when the stream is reprocessed or replayed.
Second, you can trim a stream.
When you trim a stream, you cut down the stream
to an approximate number of entries,
dropping the oldest entries in the process.
This is similar to the way in which you can trim a list.
Now let's discuss storage and delivery.
Like all other Redis data structures,
such as hashes, lists, and sets, Redis streams
are stored in memory.
But this is in contrast to Redis Pub/Sub.
Redis Pub/Sub doesn't store any data.
Instead, it delivers all data immediately
to any connected subscribers.
So Pub/Sub should really be thought
of as an ephemeral channel.
This is important to point out because Redis Pub/Sub
and Redis streams have some amount of overlap in the way
you might use them.
For instance, you might use either feature
to implement a notification system.
The difference is that with Pub/Sub, the notification
will only be delivered to connected clients,
as you can see in the diagram here.
Whereas with streams, a client may receive its notifications
whenever it connects, as the notifications will
be stored for later retrieval.
So by now, you should have a pretty good understanding
of how Redis Streams relates to other Redis data structures.
Specifically, we saw how Redis Streams compares
in the area of blocking versus non-blocking commands,
mutability, and storage and delivery.
After the quiz, we'll round out this discussion of Streams
with a working example.