The components of a distributed system
communicate via messages.
Stream processing systems process
data that comes in continuously and needs
to be analyzed in real time.
A stream processing system may consist of one or more streams
of different types.
The first type of stream is the input stream that's also
referred to as a data source.
This type of stream is usually generated
by the system's peripheral components,
its users' activities via various front ends,
or external services.
In the temperature monitoring example,
the sensors had provided the input stream.
In another application, the clickstream
of users may be the input, whereas in another,
it could be a social network's activity stream.
A stream processing system may have one or more input streams
that consists of the events that trigger the system's
activities.
Data sources provide the contents of input
streams for the system, and these are processed
by the system's components.
The results obtained from processing
the data may be delivered to some final destination
or used as input for other stream processing processes.
We use this term data sink, or sink for short,
to describe an output's final destination.
A sink may be storage of some kind or a different stream
processing system.
When stream data is written to a sink,
the system no longer cares about it and what happens to it.
It is moved outside of the system's scope.
In addition to or instead of sending the output to a sink,
the processed data can be treated as a stream
by its own right.
This stream of processed data can
be used as input for other stream processing tasks.
That's one of the most powerful concepts of stream processing --
the fact that we can use streams to store
intermediate processing results.
It lets us create pipelines made of processing steps that
are interconnected by streams of data.
Thinking about data processing as a pipeline of activities
is a pattern that both intuitively understandable
and very effective to use.
It allows implementing a complex workflow
as a series of smaller, consecutive processing steps.
When applicable, it is simpler to solve the big problem
by addressing smaller parts of it.
Doing so can also introduce asynchronicity and parallelism
in processing the data.
Stream processing systems ingest data from sources as it comes.
The ingested data is processed, and ultimately, output
is forwarded to a sink.
Some complex processing tasks can
be accomplished by chaining simpler sub
tasks, one to another, with intermediate streams
as plumbing.