In this unit, we'll discuss the context
in which Redis Streams exist.
I'll touch briefly on many topics,
and it's OK if you're not familiar with all of them.
The broad context of our discussion
is distributed systems and data processing.
In computing, we use the term distributed system
to describe a setup made up of different network components
that message each other.
In today's networked world, practically every application
is implemented as a distributed system.
Redis, for example, is designed to be a component
in a distributed system.
Its very name, Redis, is an acronym
for REmote DIctionary Server.
And remote, in this case, means that it is accessible
over the network, as opposed to a local server.
The word server also suggests its role
in the client server paradigm, a type of distributed system.
Redis the server is meant to be used
as part of a larger setup in which components communicate
with it and possibly among themselves.
Leslie B. Lamport, one of the most influencing researchers
in the domain, is attributed with the following quote.
"A distributed system is one in which
the failure of a computer you didn't even know existed
can render your computer unusable."
That quote distills some of the essential challenges
that are inherent to distributed systems.
Failures always occur, and the complex nature
of distributed systems makes reasoning about them, let alone
recovering from failures, harder.
The laws of statistics say that the more components a system is
made up of, the more likely it is for one of them
to fail at any time.
We've gotten pretty good at ensuring
the availability of stateful components,
such as storage systems and databases,
whereas virtualizations and containers make
it relatively easy to replace faulty application components.
But even though we can recover stateless components
pretty easily, recovering from their failure
is not the same thing.
The distributed system is more than just the sum
of its components, and the communication of messages in it
is an integral part of it.
When any component in a distributed system fails,
it becomes unreachable, and does not get new messages.
Furthermore, any in-flight messages
that the component may have been processing before failing
are currently lost.
The loss of a component in the distributed system
is inevitable, and therefore, the system
is designed to tolerate it.
That is, however, rarely the case
with the messages themselves.
Most distributed systems are built, as such,
to survive different types of failures
and overcome technical limitations,
all for ensuring correct processing.
Messaging is therefore a critical capability
of a distributed system.
It drives its constituent parts and changes
the system's global state.
There are many existing solutions and approaches
to distributed messaging -- that is, the management of messages
in a distributed system in a way that's reliable.
You may already be familiar with message brokers, queue managers,
and other forms of messaging and message management.
In fact, Redis is often used to power many such solutions.
Redis is a data structure server that's
ubiquitous in modern applications.
The stream data structure added to Redis in v5.0
enables distributed messaging.
Redis is an opinionated project that puts performance
and simplicity above all.
Its take on streams, while inspired by Apache Kafka's,
keeps with the project spirit and is extremely
fun and effective to use.