A distributed system relies on messaging to drive
and co-ordinate its components.
A distributed messaging system can power that
communication and often does.
Some systems are built to handle data that arrives continuously
and act quickly on changes in it.
In the era of big data, this mode of operation
is called stream processing after being popularized
by Apache Storm and merges similar concepts that
have been around before.
We turn to stream processing when
we need to act on data quickly within milliseconds
to seconds of its arrival.
Stream processing can be intuitively defined
as the opposite of batch processing.
The continuous flow of data into the system
is called the data stream -- or stream for short.
As it flows into and through a stream processing system
the system is able to pick up and act
upon the data in real time.
Temperature monitoring is perhaps
the most popular example of stream processing.
So let's use that as our starting point.
Imagine a system that alerts users whenever
the temperature outside falls within some preset range. Such
a system would consist of sensors that are deployed
at physical locations and report their readings back
to the mothership.
As the data is generated by the sensors
and streamed into the system, the system
should be able to act as fast as possible
to notify its users when needed.
Optimally, it should be able to react immediately
upon the event of getting new data.
And obviously, batch processing is not suitable for this.
The stream processing system, therefore, does not
wait for data to be batched.
Instead, it attempts to process each item
as it arrives in real time.
Furthermore, because the system is setup only once,
as opposed to a batch process that needs
to be run over and over again, it effectively
has no set up costs per process event.
This allows the system to react faster to changes.
While reaction time is the main use case for stream processing,
it does have some other useful aspects.
Stream processing is mostly concerned with recent data,
so it is typically simpler to implement,
requires fewer resources, and provides faster responses
when compared to big data warehouses and ad hoc batch
processing.
Their comparative simplicity also
makes streams easier to scale, so they
can absorb data coming in at high volumes and velocities.
Streams act in such cases as buffers in front
of other system components.
They smooth the irregularities in the influx of data,
stabilizing and protecting the system from surges.
Stream processing is a natural choice
for time series like data that comes in a never ending flow.
It is also especially useful -- and perhaps the only viable
option --
when the data set is simply too big to be stored.
Instead of attempting to store the entire data set
for processing, the firehose of raw data
can be streamed through a system that
only captures and processes the relevant bits of it.
Although the entire firehose cannot be stored,
it is possible to store and use its filtered aggregations.
On the spectrum of trade-offs, where on one end is batch
processing, on the other end lies stream processing --
a stream of changes to the data is faster and cheaper
to process than waiting for all the data to arrive.