XRANGE provides us with the means
to travel downstream, advancing from an arbitrary position
in it, towards the streams end.
There are cases, however, where the opposite direction
is called for.
For example, with a stream that keeps growing,
we may want to process just the last n messages.
Obviously, we'll need a way to "salmon" it
up and go upstream.
That's what XREVRANGE is for.
It behaves exactly like XRANGE, but accesses the stream in reverse
order.
That means that the ranges it expects are in reverse,
and in order to get the entire stream of it,
you'll need to specify the "+" and "-" special characters
in that order.
We can also easily modify our previous example
that sums the natural numbers stream to use
XREVRANGE instead of XRANGE.
Thanks to the commutative and associative laws,
and although we are summing all natural numbers
in reverse order, we still get the same result, naturally.
The last modification would be to have the summing process
stop after it completed enough iterations.
With enough being a matter of taste and choice,
the script will accept that as input.
We can sum any number of integers
as long as there are enough messages in the stream.
As shown in the example, exceeding the streams length
is perfectly harmless when handled correctly.
This manner of "wading" upstream
is suitable for producing near-real-time aggregates culled
from the end of the stream.
By sampling the latest messages, we can, for example,
calculate the average of the last n natural numbers.