Up until now, we've seen how the entire stream, as well
as discrete volumes from it, can be fetched using
both XRANGE and XREVRANGE.
Both range commands can also be used to fetch a single message.
I can use XRANGE to obtain the first message in the stream
and with XREVRANGE the last by constructing ranges
made up exclusively of the special characters "+"
and "-" and a COUNT of 1.
I can also call both range commands with any valid range.
A range made up of one message ID is perfectly OK to use.
But this requires knowing the message ID in advance somehow.
Because the message ID includes a timestamp,
you can manipulate the timestamp on your own
to specify ranges of messages corresponding
to any period of time.
Recall that the timestamp part of the message ID
is stored in milliseconds.
With proper multiplication, it should
be possible to compose ranges of any kind,
from seconds through weeks to eons and beyond.
While the range may yield any number of messages
from the stream, the same iteration patterns
apply here as well.
Stream range queries allow processing batches of messages
in a controlled manner.
They do need to be called with explicit ranges.
Let's recall the natural number sum example.
Both the downstream and the upstream variants
iterated the entire stream, or 101 messages in our case,
to obtain the result.
Now consider the case where the stream isn't static
and messages keep being produced and appended.
It is possible to use the same logic.
But as the stream grows, so will the time
it will take us to complete the computation.
Our implementation from a computational complexity
perspective is asymptotically O(n),
meaning the time it requires is linearly related
to the number of messages in the stream.
The very nature of streams implies growth.
So in our case, we'll need to find a way
to optimize the running sum algorithm.
We can improve the implementation
by storing the last processed message ID as well
as any other data, in our case the sum,
so the process can pick up from that point
with each consecutive run.
Local storage is always an option
for storing the intermediate state or any other data stored,
for that matter.
But we already have a connection to Redis,
so we can just use another key.
Let's call it "numbers:range_sum" to simply store the results
as a hash.
The first run of this modified code produces the same result
as before but stores the sum and the last known ID under
the "numbers:range_sum" hash.
We can, of course, retrieve the hash's contents for inspection
and rerun the code.
Running the same code again, however,
will result in no additional processing done as there are
no new messages in the stream.
After adding one or more messages to the stream,
the code will pick up where it left off
and add the new numbers in the message's data.
Note that I need to escape the asterisk with a backslash
to prevent the shell from interpreting it.
Also note that by implementing the running sum in this manner,
we can safely truncate the stream with MAXLEN
and still keep an accurate result
as long as the intermediate hash's contents are available.
We've seen how range queries can be
used to process a stream in an offline-like mode.
These commands allow for polling-like behavior
where a process actively retrieves and processes
the stream's messages.
Also, if we store the last processed ID and result,
range queries can be made both resilient to process failures
as well as more efficient, as only new messages will
be processed.