In this section, I'll show you how
to retrieve messages from a stream using time ranges.
The stream is a data structure, and the data
stored in it are messages.
The messages are stored by the order of their production,
and their IDs are partly made up of an ever-increasing
timestamp.
Armed with this knowledge, we can
see how to read a single message or ranges of them
or perform iteration.
To begin with, I'll recreate the numbers stream.
Instead of leaving it running indefinitely as before,
I'll use a modified version of the producer
that stops after generating exactly 101 numbers.
This is so we can have, for the time being,
a stream frozen in time.
This modified version, also for educational purposes only,
deletes the numbers stream before starting just
to be on the safe side.
Please, do not use this code in production unless you really
know what you're doing.
Back to the CLI session, we'll see
how to retrieve the stream's contents.
We've already learned about XLEN,
and we can use it to verify that the stream indeed
holds 101 messages.
The command for fetching a range of messages from a stream
is appropriately named XRANGE.
Besides the stream's "key" as the first argument,
it requires both a "start" and then "end" argument
that specify the ranges of messages
to retrieve from the stream.
In the example, I've used the special "-"
and "+" characters that are interpreted by Redis server
as the lowest and highest IDs, respectively.
As a result, the server responded
with the entire stream in ascending order, ID-wise.
Each one of the 101 messages in it
is represented in the reply as an array
with two elements -- the ID and the data.
The data in the reply is presented exactly
as it was stored, as an array of alternating field names
and values.
Or as in our case, "n" and the corresponding natural number.
It is very empowering to be able to read an entire stream but,
also, very impractical for any reason other than development,
maybe.
Programmatically speaking, we need a better way
to control the number of results returned.
We need a way to fetch the messages in chunks or pages
and be able to iterate over them one by one.
Luckily, XRANGE lets us do just that.
It just so happens that XRANGE supports an optional COUNT
argument.
We can use it to limit the number of messages
returned in the reply, as the example shows.
Also note that 0 is a perfectly valid replacement for the "-"
character.
0 is the lowest-possible partial message ID.
A partial message ID is one that consists only of the timestamp
part, no dash, and no internal sequence.
When a partial message ID is provided to XRANGE,
it is interpreted as if it was implicitly
suffixed with the lowest internal sequence.
That is 1.
So putting a 0 is shorthand for 0-1.
This use of XRANGE allows us, or rather our code,
to process a range of messages of a predetermined length
each time.
Once we're finished with the current first block
of messages, we can move on to the next one.
To proceed to process the next block of messages,
we need to call XRANGE again.
However, in this invocation, we'll
use the last message ID we've received from the previous call
and increment its sequence value by 1.
Because of the stream's strict ordering guarantees,
incrementing the last ID by 1 effectively
means that the range of messages that Redis will return
will begin with the message that immediately
follows the previous range's last message.
Like before, we'll rely on COUNT to cap the reply's length at 5.
And like before, we can take all the time
we need to process these messages before moving
on to the next set of messages.
The iteration pattern provided by XRANGE
fits the cases where we want to process the stream partially
or in its entirety in a batch-like fashion.
Depending on the use case, this pattern
is often employed to implement ad-hoc processing
for administrative and reporting purposes.
In our example of the natural numbers,
I may want to report the sum of numbers in the stream.
Any summing algorithm will process each message,
and I can use XRANGE for that.
Because the stream is frozen, my code returns with the answer.
Let's take a moment to review what we've covered thus far.
We can use XRANGE to retrieve messages based on ranges of IDs
and move forward in time from the stream's beginning
to its end in batches of any size we may need.