In this unit, we've looked at how Redis Streams
can be used to implement a logical consumer, one
that is made up of multiple instances sharing
the influx of data.
Consumer groups are the server side mechanism
that Redis provides for tracking messages
that were delivered, but not yet acknowledged.
These allow their members to consume the stream's contents
in parallel without the need for an additional synchronization
mechanism between them.
Redis' management of the Pending Entries Lists
allow each consumer to be delivered with its messages
at least once.
That once being the delivery of a new message,
but possibly more than once in cases of failures.
To stop receiving a message, the consumer
must explicitly acknowledge its processing.
The acknowledgment removes that message
from the consumer's PEL.
Although at least once is what we'd
usually prefer using as it allows us fetching
pending messages or recovery.
Consumer groups can also be used for at-most-once messaging.
In such cases, the messages and the replies sent by Redis
are considered to be automatically acknowledged,
so no PELs are maintained.
That means of course that if a message did not
get to the consumer for any reason,
or if the consumer had failed to process it,
that message will be skipped.
It is after all sent at-most-once.
This ability can be used to distribute
the processing of the workload that is allowed
to fail in part or in whole.
The way this is done in Redis is by using the optional NOACK
command with XREADGROUP.
And as usual, we can test it out in the CLI.
In the terminal window, you can inspect group one's x input
output before the XREADGROUP operation.
It has zero consumers and zero pending messages.
Recall that group one was created with the special dollar
message ID after the first message was added.
Therefore its last delivered ID is that
of the stream's first message.
Next you can see consumer 99 from group 1 making an XREADGROUP
request to get the next message like we've
seen numerous times before, but with one important difference.
It uses the no NOACK sub command to signal a server
that no acknowledgment will be sent.
The reply is what we'd expect in calling either XINFO again
or XREADGROUP with the minimal message
ID shows that there are no pending entries.
By default, consumer groups will track their consumers
pending messages until they are explicitly acknowledged
and therefore allow for messages to be sent repeatedly.
In cases where the probability for failure is relatively low
and the occasional message loss is acceptable,
consumers can turn off their tracking
with the NOACK sub command.