The consumer group is a Redis-operated mechanism
for distributing messages between members.
Consumers can join a group simply
by asking for new messages and then providing their name.
Once a consumer in a group reads messages,
these are added to its Pending Entries List.
It is up to the consumer now to actually process them.
Every consumer is different.
But ultimately, the processing of the given message
can end in either success or failure.
Like in real life, dealing with success
is much easier than coping with failure.
So let's begin with that.
To deal with success, we first need to define it.
Here's the thing.
For a consumer instance to succeed,
it needs to read the message, perhaps do some meaningful work
with the data in it, and then get to the point
where it is ready to process the next message.
Put slightly differently, in order to succeed,
the consumer needs only not to fail.
The actual work performed by the consumer and any results
obtained from it, while important in the grander scheme
of things, are outside of the scope.
Getting the message and surviving the processing
is the only measure of success in the context
of stream consumer groups.
Consumer groups provide at-least-once message delivery
semantics by default. We've seen how the consumer instance can
read its PEL, and that ability is what allows it to recover.
But when the consumer does not fail, that is,
when it succeeds processing a message,
it needs to let the server know about that.
This act, which is called acknowledgment,
is just another task among other housekeeping tasks
that the recipient does when it finishes its work.
Recall that consumerA from "group0"
requested a single message, the first message
in the natural numbers stream.
From the group's perspective, this message
is currently pending processing.
To signal that processing was completed successfully
for that message, we acknowledge it with the XACK command.
XACK is a straightforward command
that has only one form of invocation.
It accepts the name of the stream's key,
the name of the consumer group, and one or more messages IDs
that are acknowledged.
The reply returned by XACK is the number
of messages that were actually acknowledged that is
removed from the group's PEL.
The first message ID was in "consumerA"'s PEL.
Whereas the 63-79 is an ID that I made up,
so only one message was effectively removed.
It is interesting to note that XACK does not
require the consumers names, only that of the group.
While in most cases, it will be the consumer
itself doing the XACK'ing as part of its successful housekeeping,
that is not mandatory.
This liberty makes it possible for other processes
to acknowledge messages, which is definitely useful
even if only for administrative purposes.
Once we've acknowledged the message,
we can verify that "consumerA"'s PEL is now empty.
At this point, since it has no pending messages to process,
"consumerA" can issue a call to XREADGROUP
and use the greater than sign to get new messages.
To recap this pattern, a consumer group member
requests new messages but can fail at any time
before acknowledging them.
To avoid the loss of pending messages,
the consumer first reads its history of pending messages
before requesting new ones.
This provides us with at-least-once message delivery
semantics.
In this chapter, we've reviewed how the consumer group's
member operates to implement at-least-once message delivery
semantics.
Before starting, a consumer first processes messages
in its Pending Entries List and then switches
to reading new ones.
After processing a message successfully,
the server side context is updated by the consumer
explicitly by sending an acknowledgment.