The stream data structure allows order, storage, and processing
of messages.
Messages are created and stored in it by producers,
and consumers can read the messages
by iterating ranges, or one by one as they become available.
With streams, producers write to the front of data structures,
and consumers read messages from the oldest to the newest.
Multiple consumers can consume the same stream
in order to parallelize message processing.
In this video, we'll review the cases in which parallel message
processing does not provide a good solution for scaling.
Although the stream decouples the operation of consumers
and producers, the former depends on the latter, but not
visa versa.
Once producers start growing the stream,
it is possible that consumers will begin lagging behind.
This is what is called the slow consumer.
But for all intents and purposes,
it can be thought also as the fast producer.
It's all relative.
Anyway, the reason for the lag is
that the rate at which messages arrive
may be greater than the rate at which they can be processed.
Either there are too many messages
coming in, or that the time that it takes to process a message
is too long, or both.
One way to deal with this as we've
seen in the divides by two and three example,
is to employ multiple concurrent consumers that
execute sub-tasks to complete a greater shared task.
However, not all tasks can be easily refactored
to concurrent independent sub-tasks.
And even when it is possible, some of the sub-tasks
may be harder to perform, processing wise, than others.
Let's assume for a second that I possess
an extremely fast natural numbers
producer, one that can produce 100,000 numbers every second.
Let's also assume that an instance of the running sum
consumer is only capable of ingesting half that number.
Adding another consumer to assist with the running sum
will not work, because both consumer instances
will receive the same messages.
And by processing the same numbers twice,
they'll effectively double the running sum.
One way to work around this is to partition the stream.
Partitioning is basically the use of multiple keys,
each storing a subset of a logical stream.
In our example, we could have one partition
for even numbers and another for the odd numbers.
We then assign one consumer per partition.
The main problem with this approach,
however, is that we'd be creating a tight dependency
between the number of stream partitions
and the number of consumers.
If, for any reason, we require more consumers
to do our summing, or perhaps less of them,
we'd need to repartition the stream accordingly.
We'd like to avoid that, if possible.
Partitioning is a powerful pattern
for scaling the throughput of the stream's base setup,
and we'll discuss it later in more depth.
But in this case, it presents a less than desirable solution,
as it isn't dynamic enough.
The need for dynamically dividing
messages between consumers becomes even more pronounced
in use cases, where the consumers performance is
variable and non-deterministic.
Performance, which translates to execution time,
may be affected by any number of factors.
A slow network would increase the latency between the system's
components.
Or an I/O congestion would slow down the consumer, or perhaps
a busy processing core, or the availability
of some remote service.
And sometimes it is the data itself
that affects the execution time.
The fast producer, slow consumer problem is indeed challenging.
The processing of tasks that cannot be broken down
and parallellized, and ones that execute in non-deterministic
time, requires a pool of consumers,
each ingesting a subset of the stream at its own pace.
Such challenges are often managed with a queue
but Redis's streams provide built in tooling just for that.