A consumer group is made up of multiple consumers,
each of which processes a portion of the stream.
Each group is identified by name and is associated
with a single stream and the last message
ID that was delivered to the group's members.
After a consumer group is created,
members can join the group to access the stream's contents.
Joining a group is a decision made by the consumer instance.
To join and start processing messages,
all that the consumer needs to know
are the names of the stream and the group
that it wants to belong to.
This means there is no need to tell Redis beforehand
about the comings and goings of consumers.
Groups are open to any consumer that wishes to join them.
Besides the knowledge of the key and the groups' names,
in order to become a member, the instance
must provide its own name.
A consumer's name uniquely identifies that instance
among all other consumer instances in the group.
Redis will use that name to track
the consumer's progress in the group,
and we will discuss that shortly.
The consumer's name is only meaningful in the context
of a given stream and a consumer group.
As a side note refresher, Redis' CLIENT SETNAME
can be used to assign a name for the connection.
This can be quite useful when you're trying to track
and debug complex behaviors in general,
so it is considered good practice to use it.
Because consumer group members require a name,
you should consider giving them the same name as the client.
At a later time, if and when needed,
the output from CLIENT LIST will be infinitely more helpful.
That's almost all there is to it.
We've seen how a single instance consumer can
use XREAD to process a stream.
And there's a similar command called
XREADGROUP to do the same, only as part of a group.
There's also another special message ID
that you need to know about, but this is the last one.
Promise.
Let's turn to the CLI to check it out.
That's somewhat of a long command, but most of its pieces
we are already familiar with.
XREADGROUP shares with XREAD the same COUNT, BLOCK,
and STREAMS sub-commands and argument that these expect.
The first difference between the two commands,
beside their names, however, is that XREADGROUP requires
the GROUP sub-command followed by the consumer group's
name, "group0" in the example, and the consumer's name, "consumerA".
By issuing this XREADGROUP request,
"consumerA" has officially joined the group.
The second difference to notice is, as promised,
the use of a special message ID --
the greater-than sign (">").
The ">" is used exclusively by XREADGROUP.
This means the message ID that is
greater than any of the previously delivered IDs
to the group's member.
Put differently, the special ">" means,
"Give me the next undelivered message",
where "me" is a named consumer within the group.
As expected, the command returns immediately
with a reply that consists of the stream's name
and the first message in it.
Calling XREADGROUP with the ">" special message ID
is what we'd usually want to do.
After all, a single consumer's purpose is usually to process
new, yet to be delivered messages from the stream.
And that's exactly what the command does.
But messages also need to be acknowledged
by their consumers.
A message that has been delivered to one of the group's
members is said to be "pending" in the sense that it
was delivered, but its processing
is yet to be acknowledged by the consumer.
Redis keeps track of which messages
have been delivered to which consumer group members.
For that purpose, it uses an internal data
structure called the Pending Entries List, or PEL for short.
We'll discuss later how a message's state can
be changed from "pending" to something else,
or, put differently, how it can be removed from the PEL.
Under normal conditions, the removal from the PEL
is done once the consumer acknowledges
successfully processing it.
The Pending Entries List is what makes a consumer group tick.
In it, as its name suggests, are the IDs
of messages in the stream that are
pending for each consumer, along with additional metadata.
This core structure is what gives the group
its power, allowing Redis to keep tabs on the current state.
XREADGROUP can also handle partial or full message IDs.
And just like with XREAD, these are interpreted
as the non-exclusive lower bound, or the message
preceding the next one.
Unlike XREAD however, when used with the message ID,
XREADGROUP will only return messages that were already
delivered to the named consumer, effectively masking
the activity of other consumers from it
and providing it with its own unique point of view.
This masking, of course, is possible because of the PEL.
Here's how that looks like in practice.
When called by "consumerA" from "group0" again,
this time with the partial message ID 0,
we get the same first message delivered again.
The consumer in a group can only view
that part of the stream that was already delivered to it and is
yet to be processed.
The reply is effectively the entire PEL for "consumerA".
From the point of view of another consumer group
member, "consumerB", the stream currently appears to be empty.
That's the expected behavior.
"consumerB" had yet to ask for any new messages
to be delivered to it, so its PEL is empty.
Of course, "consumerB" can XREADGROUP the next message
with the ">" special message ID
and receive the stream's second message,
which contains the number 1.
It is now possible to re-run XREADGROUP for both consumers
to obtain each one's unique perspective.
We saw how XINFO GROUPS provides an overview of the stream's
groups.
Let's call it again.
This time, "group0"'s consumers value shows 2.
That value is the count of consumers
that belong to the group and accounts
for "consumerA" and "consumerB".
The group's pending value is 3.
That value is the total count of pending messages
for all consumers, or the sum of the length of their PELs.
Also note how the last delivered ID is now
set to that of "consumerB"'s message,
allowing Redis to serve the next group request from there.
Another way to inspect the state of the group's consumers
is to call XINFO with the CONSUMERS sub-command.
This form of XINFO accepts the stream's key and group names
as input, and in return, provides
a paired member breakdown.
For each consumer in the group, it
returns the PEL's length and idle time,
which is the count in milliseconds
since that consumer had last read a new message.
Members of groups have unique names that identify them.
They read undelivered messages from the stream
with the XREADGROUP command and can only
access messages that were delivered to them and not
yet processed.
Redis maintains an internal list of pending entries,
acronymed as PEL, for each consumer in the group
to track its progress.
The XINFO command allows us to inspect the stream's group
and consumers with the GROUPS and CONSUMERS sub-commands,
respectively.