A stream's consumer may lag when the rate of messages
exceeds its capacity to process them.
And some processing needs are either
hard or impossible to parallelize.
A logical consumer, that is a consumer that
is made up of a group of instances where each processes
a different message from the stream,
can be employed to distribute the workload according
to the availability of its instances.
Such a consumer is logical in the sense
that it does not really exist as an independent entity,
but is rather made up of the operation
of its constituent instances.
The logical consumer's input is the stream itself.
Each message in the stream can be
thought of as being added to a queue dedicated
to that logical consumer's instances.
Instances of the logical consumer
can then dequeue messages for processing.
Each consumer instance is therefore
served with an exclusive subset of the stream's contents,
allowing for a distribution of the workload among instances.
Redis Streams supports this pattern natively
with a feature called consumer groups.
A consumer group is an implementation
of the logical consumer for a single stream.
It can be made up of any number of physical consumers.
Consumers in a group may join or leave as needed,
which is a good fit for the needs of the dynamic setups
we've mentioned.
The Redis server keeps track of which
consumers belong to which group and the messages each
has processed.
We'll begin our group orientation
by looking at one of Redis' XGROUP command
forms of the invocation.
To create a consumer group on an existing stream,
one only needs to invoke the XGROUP command
with the CREATE sub-command, the name of the stream's key,
and the initial message ID that the group's members should
start processing from.
In this example, the first attempt to create "group0"
fails because the group's stream does not exist yet.
By adding the optional MKSTREAM sub-command let
Redis know that it is OK to create the stream even
though it has no messages in it yet.
In case, the stream already exists, Redis just
ignores that optional directive.
It is worth noting that consumer groups, unlike perhaps
any other Redis construct, must be explicitly created
with the "XGROUP CREATE" invocation.
"group0" was created using the partial message ID 0,
and just like with XREAD that ID is interpreted as 0-0.
This means that the group is poised
at the stream's very beginning before any messages in it.
So the consumers belonging to it will
start with the first message.
Let's add that first message to our natural numbers stream.
XGROUP CREATE can also be called with the special "$"
message ID, signifying that the group should begin
consumption at the next new message in the stream
exactly like how XREAD operates.
As shown in the terminal, the newly created consumer group "group1"
will start its processing at the stream's second message
being the natural number 1 that was added after its creation.
We've created two consumer groups --
"group0" and "group1" --
on the numbers stream.
"group0" was created before the streams even
existed and had triggered its creation with the MKSTREAM
command.
The group was set to begin at the partial message
ID 0 or the stream's very first message.
After adding that first message to the stream,
we created "group1" with the special dollar message ID.
This had positioned that group at the tip of the stream
after any messages already in it and just
before the next message.
There is another useful Redis command called XINFO
that, when used with the group's sub-command,
provides exactly that information and then some.
In the example's output, you can see both groups 0 and 1 as well
as their last-delivered message IDs.
The last-delivered-id of the group
is an implementation of the same approach
that we used by storing the ID in a Redis hash
with our single running sum consumer example.
We'll look into the consumers and the pending
fields in a minute or so.
So let's ignore them for now.
A Redis stream consumer group is explicitly
created and initialized with an initial message ID.
Each group consumes the stream independently from the other
with the pace of consumption being dictated
by the group's members.
In the next chapter, we'll see how consumers
join the groups for performing the equivalent of an XREAD
operation.