Welcome to week three of Redis Streams.
This week's topic is consumer groups,
which is Redis Streams' way of distributing
the consumption of a stream across multiple consumers.
In this week, we're going to cover a lot of ground,
including how to create consumer groups
and add consumers to them; how to query
the state of a consumer group; what the Pending Entries
List is and why it's important; and how
to adjust a consumer group's position in a stream.
As in chapter 1, we're providing a hands-on example
that you can run locally or in your virtual lab
to help you better understand the material.
As always, if you have any questions,
please hit us up on the forums.