In this unit, we'll look at how the memory requirements
for streams compare to other data types that could be used
to represent the same data.
We'll then move on to see why it's
important to estimate the memory required for a stream
and begin to think about how we can control that.
For many use cases with large data sets,
streams can require significantly less space
than other Redis data structures.
As we saw in the previous module,
streams are implemented using a Radix tree data
structure, an extremely efficient way
of storing key value data.
The Redis stream's implementation
contains a further optimization to reduce memory usage, field
name compression.
When multiple consecutive messages have the same field
names and are appended to the stream,
Redis will not replicate the storage of the field names.
Instead, each subsequent message having the same set
of field names is marked using a flag
rather than repeating the same field names over and over.
This means that you can save memory
by having the same structure for a series of messages
in a stream while retaining the flexibility to change
that structure over time.
Let's compare the memory used by a stream
with that required for a sorted set.
We'll experiment by storing the same data
using both data types.
The Python example code adds a configurable number of entries
to both this sorted set and a stream.
In the case of the stream, IDs begin at 1-0
and are incremented by one for each entry.
For the sorted set, scores begin at 1 for the first entry,
and are incremented for each subsequent one.
In both cases, the data stored is a simple string
"hello" plus a sequence number.
Once the entries are created, we use Redis' memory usage command
to compare the number of bytes required
to store each of the two representations of the data.
Let's run the code to generate a stream and sorted
set each containing 1,000,000 entries.
The output tells us that in this case,
the stream is substantially more memory efficient.
The sorted set takes up just over 3 and 1/2 times the memory
used by the stream implementation.
In this example, the size of our data is very small.
We're just storing the string "hello" and a number.
As the size of the data stored increases,
the relative difference in memory usage
between the sorted set and the stream implementation
will decrease.
This is because the data itself becomes
a larger percentage of the size of both data structures.
If you are choosing between whether to use a stream
or sorted set, you may wish to try a small experiment
like this and see what the space savings could
be with your own data set.
A stream processing approach is commonly
chosen when working with a data set that has the potential
to grow indefinitely.
For example, a stream of temperature readings
from a fleet of IoT sensors has no logical end to it.
Redis does not, of course, have the ability
to retain an infinitely growing data set.
A Redis server will reject write operations
when it runs out of memory.
This means that it is important to manage the size of a stream
so that it doesn't grow on forever.
Remember that consumers read from the stream,
but do not cause messages to be deleted from it once consumed.
You need to manage the stream's length separately.
When using streams, it's important to understand
how much memory you might need for your specific data
set and the options available to you to manage that.
In this unit, we saw how streams can
be more memory efficient than other data structures.
Next, we'll look at some common strategies used
to control the length of a stream
and how each can be applied to Redis Streams specifically.