Let's now take a moment to look at some performance
considerations when working with Redis streams.
We'll review the big O complexity
of some common streams commands and take a peek
under the hood to see how streams
are implemented in Redis.
The only way to add messages to a Redis stream
is by using the XADD command.
As we have seen XADD places new messages into the stream
by appending them.
No other insertion strategies are available.
So we can think of a stream as an append only log.
XADD has a time complexity of O of one, or constant time.
This means that we can expect XADD's performance
to remain the same regardless of whether we
are adding the first, hundredth, or 10 millionth
message to a stream.
In a streaming system it's important for data ingestion
to run in constant time because of the potentially large volume
of data.
Producers need to be able to add new messages into the stream
at rates not affected by the overall length of the stream.
When reading data from the stream
it's also desirable to be able to fetch one or more messages
from it with predictable performance,
ensuring consistent consumer experience regardless
of the streams length or the position of the messages in it.
When consuming from the end of the stream using
XREAD or XREADGROUP it should come as no surprise
that their performance is constant.
However, the fact that their performance remains constant
when reading from arbitrary positions
in the middle of the stream, is perhaps more noteworthy.
This holds not only for XREAD and XREADGROUP,
but also for the XRANGE and XDEL commands.
Each of these commands is able to access
any message in a stream with constant time
performance because of the way that Redis streams are
implemented.
Let's take a look into that now.
Now, it's convenient to think of a Redis stream
as an append only log, but if streams were implemented
as an append only log then many of these read operations
would have a time complexity of O of N.
So how is it that with Redis streams such operations
trend towards O of 1?
It turns out that the Redis stream data
structure is implemented as a radix tree,
an optimized trie often used to implement sets and associative
arrays.
The radix tree works by encoding keys as a set of paths
through the tree's nodes, with leaves
at the bottom representing a single key's value.
When keys share common substrings
they can be merged into a single node to save space.
This technique is called path compression.
Here we see how a series of IDs generated by XADD
might be represented in a radix tree
and how path compression can help reduce the number of nodes
required in the tree.
Common parts of the key names are merged into single nodes
with each leaf node containing a pointer
to the message payload values.
When searching a radix tree the time complexities O of M,
where M represents the length of the key being searched for.
In Redis streams key lengths, that is the message IDs,
are generally constant in length and also relatively short.
This means that all lookups have constant time complexity, which
can be reduced to O of 1.
One thing to keep in mind however,
even though locating a key is an O of 1 operation,
scanning from that key onwards is still
O of N on the number of messages returned.
For example, running an XRANGE command
with a counter argument of a million
is still O of a million.
So in general be careful with the count argument when running
XRANGE, XREAD, and XREADGROUP.
It's hard to make a rule of thumb here,
but if you need more than 1,000 messages returned,
it's probably best to break this into multiple calls.
Anecdotally, when I try returning a million messages
from a stream on my local machine it takes 90 seconds.
And that's a long time for a Redis server to be blocked.
Anyway if you'd like to learn more about this specific radix
tree implementation used for Redis streams,
check out the RAX project on GitHub,
which is a standalone implementation of it.
So what's the upshot here?
Well, unlike an actual append only log,
fetching or deleting an ID from your Redis stream
is a constant time operation.
This is because Redis streams are
implemented using radix trees.
Any operation that involves seeking to a particular point
in the stream is O of 1.
But still be careful to avoid returning thousands of messages
or more in a single call.
This is expensive no matter what the underlying data structure
you use.
But overall you have a lot more flexibility
in reading your Redis stream than you
have in scanning a traditional append only log
and you can use this to your advantage
when designing Redis streams applications.