In this unit, we'll review a few important Redis Streams usage
patterns.
First, we'll talk about how to deal with large payloads.
Next, we'll consider the trade-offs
between having one large stream and many smaller streams.
And finally, we'll talk about when
to use a single consumer versus consumer groups.
There are a couple of techniques you
can use to handle streams whose messages are large.
Large is, of course, relative, but keep in mind
that no single stream can use more memory
than is available on any single Redis server.
For example, suppose I have a stream whose messages
are 50 kilobytes in size.
Once the stream is a million messages in length,
that's 50 gigabytes.
And that might be larger than any of our Redis servers.
So what are the solutions to this?
Well, first, there's stream trimming,
which we discussed earlier.
But second, you can consider storing
the large payload outside of the stream itself
and referencing it from the stream.
If the payload needs to be hot in memory
but doesn't always have to be accessed within the stream,
then store it in a secondary Redis data
structure, such as a hash.
If you're running a clustered Redis deployment,
these payloads will naturally distribute across the cluster.
But for especially large payloads
that don't need to be in memory, consider
storing these on disk or in an external large object store.
Let's now talk about the single stream
versus multiple streams question.
When using Redis streams, we often
need to decide between using one large stream
or multiple smaller streams to represent a domain.
The answer to this dilemma often depends
on the stream's access patterns, or how you're
going to access the stream.
Let's take the example of user notifications.
Typically, a user has a mailbox of notifications,
and we need to be able to view all of the latest notifications
for a single user.
For this case, one stream per user notification mailbox
makes the most sense.
We can then view the latest notifications for that user
with a call to XREVRANGE.
An example of a single global stream
might be an API access log.
Suppose we have tens of thousands
of users all hitting our public API.
Each API access is an event in the stream.
If our goal is to be able to analyze the overall usage
patterns, then a single stream for all API access events
makes the most sense.
Another point to consider here--
with many smaller streams, these can
be partitioned across nodes in a Redis cluster.
With one large stream, you'll need
to be more careful to cap the stream so
that it doesn't take up all the memory on a single server.
This is true even if you're running a clustered Redis
deployment.
OK, lastly, let's tackle the question
of when to use a single consumer versus consumer groups.
To review, the single consumer involves
using XREAD to process the stream in order.
While doing so, you need to keep track of your last processed
ID, possibly storing that ID in Redis.
The consumer group pattern involves
a few different commands, and we described this in detail
last week.
Let's start with consumer groups.
There are two scenarios where consumer groups make the most
sense.
The first is when you need out-of-order processing.
For example, suppose each event in a stream
represents a photo that requires processing.
Suppose further that we have a set of microservices that can
process 10 photos at a time.
With XREADGROUP, we can send 10 messages at a time
to the microservice, and then XACK each message as soon
as the photo it points to has completed processing.
So we don't have to do this out-of-order accounting
on our own.
The second case for consumer groups
is when processing each message requires significant CPU.
Suppose we're doing text classification.
We need to fan this out to multiple processes/threads/CPUs
to keep up with the growth of the stream.
To solve this, we create a consumer group,
with one consumer per thread per process,
across, perhaps, a cluster of machines.
Now, if you don't need out-of-order processing,
or if your processing isn't too computationally expensive
for a single consumer, then it's best
to opt for XREAD with a single consumer.
And here's a really important point to remember.
Even if you need stream segmentation,
you can still accomplish this using a single consumer
with XREAD.
To do this, each consumer simply needs to keep track of its own
offset in the stream.
Here's a diagram with three consumers
on the same stream using XREAD.
Here, each consumer is writing its last processed ID
into a separate Redis key.
If one of these consumers ever goes offline,
it must read this last processed ID
and start from there when it comes back online.
So in this unit, we saw some important Redis
Streams usage patterns.
Understanding these patterns will
help you make good design decisions
when building a system on Redis Streams.