In this unit, we'll revisit three strategies
for capping a stream's length.
First, we'll see how a producer can manage the stream's length
using XADD.
Next, we'll look at using XTRIM to cap the stream.
And finally, we'll learn a technique
for capping a stream based upon its age.
The first approach is to explicitly cap
the stream's length when producing to the stream.
When adding messages to the stream with XADD,
you can specify the MAXLEN subcommand.
This command tells Redis to add new messages
and also remove the oldest existing messages as needed,
keeping the stream at the requested length.
An advantage of this strategy is that the stream's growth
is tightly controlled.
It results in frequent checking of the stream's length
against the desired length, as these
are compared on every insert into the stream.
This approach can also be used without adding
additional components of the system,
as the capping is performed by existing producers.
The strategy does, however, incur the performance
hit associated with checking the stream's length
and potentially trimming it on every call to XADD.
To mitigate this, you can provide the tilde option
with MAXLEN, which will cause the stream's length
to be trimmed to approximately the number of specified
entries.
When the tilde modifier is used, Redis
will only trim messages when it can remove a whole node
from the underlying radix tree.
This is more efficient than partial removal
of the nodes entries, which is what's
required when an exact MAX length is requested.
We recommend that you use the tilde approximation approach,
in general.
This uses fewer server resources,
freeing Redis to service other requests faster,
while still ensuring that the length of your stream
remains approximately within the bounds
that you have chosen for it.
The second stream management strategy to consider
is similar to the first in that it involves periodically
trimming the stream's length.
The difference is that it can be performed independently
of a stream producer or a consumer,
for example, by a management component
or by an administrator.
The XTRIM command is used to cap the stream's length and works
in the same way as XADD's MAXLEN command.
Like MAXLEN, XTRIM can be used to cap
the stream to an exact length or to an approximate length.
You should use the strategy if you
wish to cap the stream periodically,
rather than as a function of the operation of a producer.
This strategy can be implemented manually as an administrator
or by using some other component that
monitors the stream, capping only when its length exceeds
your chosen threshold.
But sometimes you want to manage the stream's contents by time,
rather than by overall length.
There's currently no built-in method to trim a stream by time
range--
for example, to remove entries more than a week old.
If your application requires this,
you should consider partitioning the stream by date/time
and expiring partitions periodically using Redis'
EXPIRE command.
Let's take a look at how that might work.
One way to achieve time-based expiry
is by partitioning a stream by date/time.
This way, we can either delete old partitions manually.
Or we can auto expire them using the EXPIRE command.
For example, we might partition by day using a year, month, day
pattern to name each partition.
The producer would then write to the current partition
for the day, and consumers would read from it.
Implementing this strategy requires both producers
and consumers to implement the application specific logic
for the naming of stream partitions
and to know when to begin writing to and reading
from them.
Some consumer read activities may
need to be performed over multiple partitions
of the stream.
Redis streams provides some assistance
with implementing such a strategy.
The XADD command will create a stream
if it doesn't already exist, saving
the need for an explicit creation
step for each new partition.
And because Redis streams are implemented as a regular data
type that exists in the main key space,
the EXPIRE command can be used to remove stream partitions
after a given time period is passed.
We'll see an implementation of this strategy in this week's
hands-on activity.
The stream management strategies outlined in this unit
rely on controlling the stream's growth by managing
the number of messages in it.
In common with other Redis data structures,
a stream's overall bite size and memory cannot be directly
limited.
If you wish to size your stream such that it takes up
an approximate amount of memory, then you
will need to understand the average size of your message
payloads and trim by length accordingly.
If you can estimate the number of messages per day,
then you can use some of the strategies described
in the previous unit to estimate the size of your stream.
When using streams, it's important to understand
how much memory you might need for your specific data
set and the options available for you to manage that.
In this unit, we reviewed some strategies
for controlling a stream's size over time.
When using streams, it's likely that you'll
need to use a mix of these strategies,
depending on your application's use case.