Welcome to Week 4 of RU202--
Redis Streams.
Last week we focused on strategies
for consuming messages from a stream using consumer groups.
The goal of this week is to discuss
the real-world considerations you
need to think about when running Redis Streams in production.
We'll begin this week by studying
how to deal with the failure of a consumer.
Next we'll go over stream performance and stream memory
management.
We'll also spend some time summarizing
the most common Redis Streams usage patterns.
You'll want to pay close attention to these patterns,
because they bring together everything you should
have learned in this course.
Finally, we'll apply the concepts
we've learned to build out parts of an application using
Redis Streams.
Using Python, we'll implement a set of producers and consumers
that work together to manage and process
an incoming stream of data.
By the end of the week, you'll have worked on your first Redis
Streams application, and you'll be
ready to start integrating Redis Streams into your own systems.