Last week, we finished off with a discussion
of the difficulties that can be involved
in safely deleting the individual consumers
of a group.
In this chapter, we're going to look at two commands, XPENDING
and XCLAIM, and how they can be used when
a consumer from a group fails.
Now, in a perfect world, consumers
would always acknowledge the messages delivered to them.
But if you've spent any time working with stream processing
systems, you know that this isn't always the case.
It's always possible for a consumer to receive a message
and then go offline before the message can be acknowledged.
When that happens, there will be at least one message
in the consumer's Pending Entries List.
If that's the case, we need a way
of getting that stranded message to a consumer that
can effectively process and acknowledge it.
To see how we do that, let's return again
to the natural numbers stream.
In this example, I've cleared out all of the consumer groups
we created last week.
So let's start by creating a group called
evens that starts at the beginning of the stream.
Let's next create two consumers, A and B, each consuming
a single message.
For consumer B, we'll acknowledge the message
that it just consumed.
So now what's the state of the consumer group?
Running XINFO GROUPS, you can see here
that we have two consumers.
We also have one pending message.
That should be no surprise.
We can run XINFO CONSUMERS to find out where that pending
message lives.
And you can see here that it must belong to consumer A,
as consumer B has no pending messages.
Now, suppose that consumer A has gone offline.
In this case, we need a way to reassign its pending messages.
There are two commands that can help with this, XPENDING
and XCLAIM.
Let's start with XPENDING.
In its most basic form, XPENDING takes two arguments,
the name of the stream and the name of a consumer group.
Let's run XPENDING on our numbers stream and evens group.
Check out the output.
First, we get the total number of pending messages.
Next, we can see the range of message IDs
in the Pending Entries List.
We also get to see how many pending entries per consumer
exist.
As we saw earlier, consumer A has one pending entry.
But what does that entry look like?
To get that information, we need to run XPENDING with a few more
arguments.
The next variant of the XPENDING command
takes a range of message IDs and a count.
As with XRANGE, here we can use the special minus
and plus operators to iterate the entire range of pending
IDs.
When we do that, we can learn a bit more about the pending
message ID currently assigned to consumer A.
Here we see the message ID, the name of the consumer it's assigned
to, the number of milliseconds elapsed since it was delivered
to the consumer, and a delivery counter, which,
as you might expect, records the number of times
the message has been delivered.
One thing to note here is that the time since delivery field
will be reset each time the consumer reads this message.
Thus, we can run the following XREADGROUP command.
When we run XPENDING again, you'll
notice that the time since delivery field has been reset.
So what does XPENDING do for us?
Effectively, it gives us more information
about the currently pending entries for our consumer group.
Specifically, it gives us the IDs of the pending messages,
the number of times each message has been read by the consumer,
and the elapsed time since the message was last delivered.
So suppose we've decided to reassign the pending
message from consumer A to consumer
B. We'll need to use the XCLAIM command.
In its most basic usage, the XCLAIM command
takes four arguments, the stream name, the consumer group name,
the name of the consumer claiming the message,
and a min idle time.
XCLAIM will succeed only if the elapsed time
since the last delivery of the message
is greater than this min idle time.
This gives you an automatic way of preventing XCLAIM
from claiming a message that hasn't had
a chance to be processed yet.
So to claim A's pending message for B,
we run the command like so.
When successful, XCLAIM returns the message that was claimed,
as you can see here.
If we quickly run XPENDING, we'll
see that the message is now indeed owned by consumer B.
Now, here are some things you need to know about the XCLAIM
command.
First, any Redis client can claim a message
on behalf of a consumer using XCLAIM.
This means that you can have an out of band process
that monitors consumer groups and reassigns pending messages
as necessary.
Second, claiming a message resets the elapsed time
since delivery and increments the delivery count by one.
Third, if you want to reset the delivery counter,
use XCLAIM's RETRYCOUNT option.
This allows you to set the counter to zero, for instance,
on an XCLAIM.
So to summarize, the XPENDING and XCLAIM commands,
combined with XINFO, give you the ability to detect and then
reassign messages from one consumer's Pending Entries List
to another's.
In the next unit, we'll talk about consumer recovery
scenarios in a bit more detail.