Now that you understand XPENDING and XCLAIM,
let's think about some consumer recovery scenarios.
When exactly do you need to recover a Redis Streams
consumer?
And what exactly does recovery mean?
Basically, if you want at-least-once delivery
semantics, and you lose a consumer from a group,
then you need to ensure that the messages from that consumer's
PEL or pending entries list are reassigned.
After all, we can't guarantee that a consumer
has processed a message until it has acknowledged the message.
Now how does a consumer become unavailable?
There are many possibilities.
But it's usually due to the loss of a VM or a container.
There are, of course, cases where we've intentionally
removed the consumer.
Either way, it's important to remember
that Redis does not automatically recover
unacknowledged messages.
That's the job of the Redis user.
Now if you've been following along,
you should have some idea about how this might be implemented.
Providing a full implementation of this
is beyond the scope of this course.
But what it amounts to is this.
One, continuously monitoring pending messages.
This means frequent calls to the XPENDING command.
Two, deciding upon a heuristic for when
a message should be assigned to a different consumer.
Some combination of message delivery count,
time since delivery, and how long a consumer is idle
will figure into this calculation.
Three, deciding how to reassign messages.
Are they reassigned to other consumers randomly
or in a round-robin fashion or to the consumer with the lowest
idle time?
Now we'd be remiss if we didn't discuss one other failure
scenario to be prepared for.
And that is the poison-pill message.
A poison-pill is a message that's effectively
unprocessable, preventing consumers
from ever acknowledging it.
In the worst cases, such messages
cause a consumer process to die.
But in other cases, they may trigger
bugs that cause a consumer's load to spike,
thus rendering the consumer unavailable.
You can imagine that if you had an automated recovery
strategy as I just described, you'd
also want to think about the possibility
of a poison-pill message.
After all, such a message can wreak havoc on a system
as it's assigned from one consumer to the next.
So it may be important to detect the case where a message is
continuously being reassigned.
In other words, you may want to keep track of how many times
the same message has been XCLAIMED.
This may indicate the presence of the dreaded poison-pill.
In summary, Redis gives you the primitive commands
that you need to implement some basic recovery strategies.
If you need consumer groups and want
to build a resilient at-least-once delivery system,
then you'll want to spend some time
experimenting with these commands
and simulating failure and recovery scenarios.