[CHILDREN PLAYING]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[BELL RINGING]
Hello.
And welcome to Redis University.
We're so happy you've signed up for this class.
We hope you gain as many insights and techniques
as you need to get the most out of Redis.
But before we dive into the course content, let's
deal with some logistics first.
Each course is broken down into a series of chapters.
Each chapter is made up of between 30 and 45 minutes
of videos to review.
The videos are 5 to 7 minutes in length,
with quizzes at the end of each to help
you check your understanding.
At the end of each chapter, there
may be labs and homework questions for you to complete.
The labs aren't graded, but the homework questions are.
Depending on the course and you're
familiarity with the material, you
should expect to spend anywhere from 1 to 2 hours
on each week's videos, labs, and homework questions.
Now keep in mind that you're not alone in taking this course.
Along with the other students enrolled in the course,
our teachers and other engineers are
available to help if you get stuck
or need more clarification.
Just click on the discussion tab,
head over to our Discord server, will be
there to answer your questions.
Most of our courses have a public GitHub repo
containing all of the example code
on how to set up a lab environment at home.
It's here that we'll also provide instructions
for setting up your own Redis server,
whether that's by launching a Docker instance
or compiling their Redis code base and running it locally.
Now all the homework questions count towards your final grade.
And during the last week of the course,
you'll be given a final exam.
50% of your final grade will come from each chapter's
homework questions.
And the remaining 50% will come from the score
on your final exam.
You'll need to score a 65% or better
to get a certification of completion.
Of course, let's not let grades get in the way of learning.
Most of all, we want to ensure that you have a fun
and engaging learning experience.
So jump into the discussion, say Hi,
and provide us with any feedback you might have.
Thanks again for joining this course.
We're excited to have you here, and we wish you all the best
in your Redis learning journey.
[MUSIC PLAYING]