Hey there, and welcome to Redis University.
This is RU202 Redis Streams.
As you probably well know, streaming is everywhere now.
Social media feeds, sensors, and IoT devices in the field
are just a few examples of the systems now generating
multitudes of data in real-time.
To process this data, what's needed
are robust streaming primitives.
Redis Streams is a new feature of Redis that provides this.
In this course, we're going to teach you
everything you need to know to start being
successful with Redis Streams.
In week one, we'll provide an introduction
to distributed systems, messaging,
and streaming pipelines.
This will provide you with some of the background that
motivated the design of Redis Streams.
We'll then go over Redis Streams describing
the high-level features and providing a working example.
In weeks two and three, we'll be drilling down
into the guts of Redis Streams.
Week two covers producers, consumers,
and queries against streams.
In week three, we delve into one of Redis Streams most powerful
features, consumer groups.
Finally, in week four, we'll show
a number of best practices and patterns
for using Redis Streams to solve real problems.
We'll also review stream administration and management.
To get the most out of this course,
you'll want to have a good understanding of Redis
with some experience working with basic Redis data
structures.
If you don't have much background,
you may want to consider enrolling in RU101,
our introductory Redis course.
As with all of our courses, if you have any questions,
please reach out to the teaching assistants
on the course forums, and you'll get the help you need.
Again, welcome to Redis Streams.
We're thrilled to have you along and we sincerely
hope you enjoy the course.