So by now, you should have a good idea
about how to scale the consumption of streams
using consumer groups.
But how do you manage consumer groups in the longer term?
Let's start to answer that question
by looking at some important consumer group administration
tasks.
First, we'll learn how to change a consumer group's
position in the stream.
Second, we'll learn how to delete a consumer group.
And finally, we'll learn how to remove an individual consumer
from a consumer group, and some of the important considerations
surrounding this.
To illustrate these operations, let's
go back to our natural numbers stream and create a few groups.
First, we'll create a group called
"primes" that starts at the end of the stream.
Next, we'll create a group called
"sums" that starts at ID 0, or the beginning of the stream.
Finally, let's create another group
called "averages" that also starts at the beginning of the stream.
We'll also create a few consumers
for the averages group.
Consumer "A" has consumed two messages
without acknowledging them.
Consumers "B" and "C" have both consumed a single message,
and have acknowledged that message.
Now, we need to talk about changing a consumer group's
position.
Here's a diagram representing the numbers stream,
and the three consumer groups we've just created.
The primes consumer group is currently
at the end of the stream, while the sums and averages consumer
groups are at the beginning.
We can confirm this by running a couple of XINFO commands.
When we run XINFO GROUPS, we can see the last delivered ID
for each consumer group.
For primes, it's a very specific ID.
In fact, when we run XINFO STREAM numbers,
we see that the last entry ID is the same as the primes consumer
group's last delivered ID.
So the upshot is that consumer groups always
have a specific position in the stream that's dictated
by their last entry ID.
When consuming a stream, the consumers in a group
will receive messages whose IDs start after the last entry ID.
So if we want to change a consumer's
position in the stream, we need to alter this last entry ID.
For that, we can use XGROUP's SETID sub-command.
For example, suppose we eventually
decide that we want the primes consumer group to start
reading from the beginning of the stream
instead of from the end.
We simply run this command.
If we want to position the group at an arbitrary ID,
we can do that too.
Or we can place the consumption back
at the end of the stream using the special dollar sign ID.
The use cases here should be obvious.
Either we want to replay a stream from the beginning,
or we want to start consumption from somewhere in the middle --
perhaps at a specific timestamp.
Or we want to start consuming the stream from this moment
onward, only processing new messages from here on out.
Now, let's learn how to delete a consumer group.
It's first important to remember that Redis does not clean up
unused consumer groups, so we need a way to clean them up
on our own.
Maybe we're done with a particular consumer group,
or perhaps we accidentally created it.
Either way, the XGROUP DESTROY command
will permanently remove the specified consumer group
and any associated consumers, so you
need to use this command with some care.
Here's how to use it.
Suppose we decide we're done with the sums consumer group.
We simply run XGROUP DESTROY, specifying the stream
name and the group name.
So here we run XGROUP DESTROY numbers sums,
and that's all there is to it.
Now, in addition to removing entire consumer groups,
we can also remove individual consumers from a group.
There are a number of reasons why we might want to do this.
One is that the system running the consumer no longer exists.
Perhaps we're having a downtime, or some kind of outage,
or we've lost a VM.
Or perhaps we're simply scaling down our consumption
and don't need as many consumers as we used to.
Whatever the reason, consumers themselves are easy to delete.
We simply use the XGROUP DELCONSUMER command,
passing in the name of the stream, the name of the group,
and the name of the consumer.
For example, here's how to delete consumer "C"
from the averages consumer group.
This command returns the number of pending entries
owned by the deleted consumer.
Consumer "C" had zero pending entries.
That's straightforward, and it's perfectly safe
to do when the consumer's pending entries list is empty,
as in this case.
But to delve a bit deeper here, let's
take a look at the remaining consumers for the averages
group.
You'll notice that consumer A has two pending entries.
As pending entries, these entries
have not been acknowledged by the consumer.
If we delete this consumer, we won't
know if they've been processed correctly.
This is a potentially common scenario.
You may find yourself in a situation
where a VM hosting a consumer goes offline,
all while its consumers still have pending entries.
If you want those pending entries
to be consumed and acknowledged, then you'll
need to assign them elsewhere before deleting the consumer.
How do you do that?
The short answer is that you use a combination of the XCLAIM
and XPENDING commands, which we'll discuss next week.
For now, be careful when deleting individual consumers,
and understand the consequences of deleting consumers
with pending entries.
So in this unit, you learned how to change a consumer group's
position in the stream, delete a consumer group as a whole,
and delete individual consumers.
You also learned that you need to be careful
when deleting consumers that have pending entries.
And hopefully this got you curious about the consumer
group recovery strategies that we'll be discussing next week.