Congratulations on making it to the end of week 3.
By now, you should know enough about consumer groups
to start thinking about how you might use them
in your applications.
We started off with an overview of the consumer scaling problem
and presented consumer groups as a possible solution.
We then described how to create groups and add consumers.
Hopefully you had a chance to try the hands-on exercise.
We then finished the week by describing
at-most-once delivery with consumer groups,
along with some basic administrative commands.
Next week, we'll touch on quite a few topics.
These will include ways to handle consumer failures,
the scaling of streams, performance considerations,
and capacity planning.
We'll also work on a complete real-world example.
See you next time.